Preliminary Guide to the George Steiner papers, 1955-1994 MS2279.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Steiner papers
1955-1994
1960-1985
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Dept. of Music
Steiner, George
MS2279.UA
12 Linear Feet 8 record cartons
George Steiner was a violinist, conductor, administrator, teacher, and founder of the George Washington University's music department. The collection dates from 1955 to 1994, with the bulk of the material dating between 1960 and 1985. It includes programs, program notes, clippings, lecture and teaching files, correspondence, music manuscript, minutes, surveys, press releases, and television scripts. Subjects include the George Washington University Music Department, the Alexandria Symphony Orchestra, Washington Camerata Orchestra, The Friday Morning Music Club Orchestra, the National Association of Schools of Music, and Music Teachers National Association.
Scope and Contents
The papers of George Steiner consist of materials that document Steiner's career as a musician, conductor, and educator. The collection dates from 1955 to 1994, with the bulk of the material dating between 1960 and 1985. It includes programs, program notes, clippings, lecture and teaching files, correspondence, music manuscript, minutes, surveys, press releases, and television scripts. Subjects include the George Washington University Music Department, the Alexandria Symphony Orchestra, Washington Camerata Orchestra, The Friday Morning Music Club Orchestra, the National Association of Schools of Music, and Music Teachers National Association. This collection is minimally processed and may not be available for research. Please contact Special Collections for more information.
Biographical / Historical
George Steiner was a violinist, conductor, administrator, teacher, and founder of the George Washington University's music department.
Born in Baltimore in 1918, Steiner began playing the violin at age 6, and gave his first public performance at age 7. At age 15 he conducted the Baltimore City College Orchestra. He earned a Bachelor of Science and Bachelor of Music (1938) at the Johns Hopkins University, and a Master's in Music from the Peabody Conservatory (1940). He served in the Navy during World War II as a radar officer in the Pacific, and returned to Washington, D.C. in 1949 as concertmaster of the National Symphony Orchestra.
During the 1950s, Steiner also acted as the concertmaster for the National Gallery Orchestra, pursued graduate studies in musicology at Catholic University, and taught classes at American University where he played in the school's string quartet and conducted the university's Chamber Music Society and Contemporary Music Symposium.
In 1960 Mr. Steiner was appointed to the faculty of the George Washington University where he founded the university's music department. As chairman of the department, Steiner established undergraduate and graduate degree programs accredited by the National Association of Schools of Music, hired music faculty, and secured space for the department in the University Academic Center. He also taught violin and music history, and conducted chamber ensembles. Mr. Steiner resigned as chairman of GWU's music department in 1983, and in 1984 the Steiner Music Scholarship was established in his name. He was given emeritus status in 1988, and taught at the George Washington University until 2007.
George Steiner conducted many ensembles throughout his career. In 1966 he became the music director for the Alexandria Symphony Orchestra. Mr. Steiner also directed the Washington Camerata Orchestra and the Friday Morning Music Club Orchestra. He was a soloist and guest conductor with many orchestras, and he directed, produced, and performed in many television programs and movie soundtracks.
He received many honors throughout his lifetime including the National Symphony Orchestra's Special Citation for Distinguished Service to the Washington Music Community (1953), The Distinguished Alumnus Award from The Johns Hopkins University (1973) and the Distinguished Washington Educator Award (1987).
George Steiner died on December 29, 2008 at the age of 90.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the George Washington University Department of Music, 2009 (2009.070).
Arrangement
This collection is unprocessed and is in the order in which it was received. Please contact Special Collections staff for assistance.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Some material may be restricted. Access to student records is governed by the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), which protects the privacy of student education records. Student records in this collection are closed for 100 years from date of record creation. Please see Special Collections staff for assistance.
Music teachers -- Washington (D.C.); Music -- Washington (D.C.); Conductors (Music) -- Washington (D.C.); Musicians; Musicians -- Washington (D.C.); George Washington University. Dept. of Music; Alexandria Symphony Orchestra; National Association of Schools of Music; Music Teachers National Association; George Washington University. Mount Vernon Campus; Friday Morning Music Club (Washington, D.C.)
- Alexandria Symphony Orchestra, circa 1975-1979 (Box UP0001, Folder 1)
- Alexandria Symphony Orchestra, mid- to late-60's and early-70's, circa 1965-1969 and 1975-1979 (Box UP0001, Folder 2)
- Program Notes, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 3)
- Alexandria Symphony Orchestra, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 4)
- Alexandria Symphony Board of Directors 86-87, 1986-1987 (Box UP0001, Folder 5)
- Alexandria General, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 6)
- Youth Programs, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 7)
- Alexandria Programs 1983-1987 (Box UP0001, Folder 8)
- Alexandria Symphony Orchestra, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 9)
- Letters to George Steiner and news clippings re: Lois Flannery's death, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 10)
- Alexandria Symphony Orchestra "A Gourmet Season", undated (Box UP0001, Folder 11)
- M. W. Th. Class 3, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 12)
- Alexandria Symphony Orchestra '84-'85, 1984-1985 (Box UP0001, Folder 13)
- Letter to orchestra Members, Letter of position offer, Board Meeting notice, Meeting Minutes, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 14)
- Introduction to the Alexandria Symphony Orchestra, Press release, Grand Finale announcement, '82-'83, 1982-1983 (Box UP0001, Folder 15)
- Alexandria Symphony Orchestra Programs 1966-78, 1966-1978 (Box UP0001, Folder 16)
- Alexandria Symphony Orchestra Programs 1978-82, 1978-1982 (Box UP0001, Folder 17)
- Composer Catalogues, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 18)
- For Kathleen Baker - The Alexandria Symphony, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 20)
- Composer Catalogs (Ernst Krenek - Ernest Bloch), Musical Merchandise Catalogs, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 21)
- Programs, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 22)
- Programs, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 23)
- Programs, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 24)
- Miscellaneous clippings, undated (Box UP0001, Folder 25)
- TV Show 1967-1968 (Box UP0002, Folder 1)
- TV Script I, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 2)
- TV Script II, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 3)
- TV Script 3, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 4)
- TV Script 4, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 5)
- TV Script 5, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 6)
- Music Transparencies, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 7)
- TV Color- Duo Recital, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 8)
- Radio Lectures in Miniature, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 9)
- WGMS Script, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 10)
- TV General, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 11)
- Papers (1), undated (Box UP0002, Folder 12)
- Papers (2), undated (Box UP0002, Folder 13)
- untitled, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 14)
- Humanities, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 15)
- Music 104- papers retained, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 16)
- Music 103- papers retained, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 17)
- Chamber music lit- papers retained, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 18)
- untitled 2, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 19)
- Orchestra literature, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 20)
- Orchestra literature, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 21)
- Orchestra literature, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 22)
- Orchestra literature, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 23)
- 20th Century, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 24)
- 20th Century, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 25)
- 20th Century, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 26)
- music instruments, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 27)
- Opera 121, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 28)
- Pedagogy, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 29)
- the 3 B'ees, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 30)
- miscellaneous, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 31)
- elements, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 32)
- Harmony, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 33)
- Romance 107, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 34)
- Music 125, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 35)
- Classic Period, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 36)
- History of Music 104-Quizzes and exams, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 37)
- History of Music 104, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 38)
- History of Music 104, undated (Box UP0002, Folder 39)
- Blueprints of Music Dept. and music manuscript, undated (Box UP0003, Folder 1)
- Grade Sheets, Recital programs, graded papers and tests, more grade sheets, undated (Box UP0003, Folder 2)
- Staff Paper, national music council bulletin, newspaper clippings, magazine clippings, Ive's festival, Music at Yale quarterly report, empty envelopes, undated (Box UP0003, Folder 3)
- Alumni Mailing List, undated (Box UP0003, Folder 4)
- Festival Ideas and newspaper clippings, undated (Box UP0003, Folder 6)
- Music Programs - completed 1961-1962 (Box UP0003, Folder 7)
- Music Programs - completed 1962-1963 (Box UP0003, Folder 8)
- Music Programs - completed 1963-1964 (Box UP0003, Folder 9)
- Music Programs - completed 1964-1965 (Box UP0003, Folder 10)
- Music Departmental 1965-1966 (Box UP0003, Folder 11)
- Music Departmental 1966-1967 (Box UP0003, Folder 12)
- Music Departmental 1967-1968 (Box UP0003, Folder 13)
- Music Departmental 1968-1969 (Box UP0003, Folder 14)
- Music Departmental 1969-1970 (Box UP0003, Folder 15)
- Music Departmental 1970-1971 (Box UP0003, Folder 16)
- Annual Reports, undated (Box UP0003, Folder 17)
- Music Departmental 1971-72, 1971-1972 (Box UP0003, Folder 18)
- Music Departmental 1973-74, 1973-1974 (Box UP0003, Folder 19)
- Music Departmental 1972-73, 1972-1973 (Box UP0003, Folder 20)
- Music Departmental 1974-75, 1974-1975 (Box UP0003, Folder 21)
- Music Departmental 1975-76, 1975-1976 (Box UP0003, Folder 22)
- Music Departmental 1976-77, 1976-1977 (Box UP0003, Folder 23)
- Friday Morning Music Club, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 1)
- Friday Morning Music Club 1966-1967 (Box UP0004, Folder 2)
- Friday Morning Music Club, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 3)
- Friday Morning Music Club 1968-1969 (Box UP0004, Folder 4)
- Friday Morning Music Club 1967-1968 (Box UP0004, Folder 5)
- Friday Morning Music Club 1969-1970 (Box UP0004, Folder 6)
- Washington Camerata, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 7)
- Potomac, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 8)
- Musical Activity Community 1955-1966 (Box UP0004, Folder 9)
- Musical Activity Community 1966-1967 (Box UP0004, Folder 10)
- Musical Activity Community 1967-1968 (Box UP0004, Folder 11)
- Musical Activity Community 1968-1969 (Box UP0004, Folder 12)
- Programs, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 13)
- Envelope, 1961 Symposium Material (Box UP0004, Folder 14)
- Washington Camerata programs, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 15)
- American University Orchestra, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 16)
- Publicity 1961 (Box UP0004, Folder 17)
- Glossary I '94, 1994 (Box UP0004, Folder 18)
- Harvard List II, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 19)
- Publicity, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 20)
- Duplicate (from '62 pub.), 1962 (Box UP0004, Folder 21)
- Publicity 1962 (Box UP0004, Folder 22)
- Publicity 1963 (Box UP0004, Folder 23)
- Publicity 1964 (Box UP0004, Folder 24)
- Publicity 1965-1966 (Box UP0004, Folder 25)
- Publicity 1966-1967 (Box UP0004, Folder 26)
- Publicity 1967-1968 (Box UP0004, Folder 27)
- Publicity 1968-1969 (Box UP0004, Folder 28)
- Publicity 1969-1970 (Box UP0004, Folder 29)
- Publicity, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 30)
- National Association of Schools of Music, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 31)
- untitled 3, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 32)
- Conducting, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 33)
- Conducting (2), undated (Box UP0004, Folder 34)
- Conducting (3), undated (Box UP0004, Folder 35)
- untitled 4, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 36)
- untitled 5, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 37)
- TV 10, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 38)
- TV 11, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 39)
- TV 12, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 40)
- TV 13, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 41)
- TV 14, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 42)
- TV 6, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 43)
- TV 7, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 44)
- TV 8, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 45)
- TV 9, undated (Box UP0004, Folder 46)
- National Associations of Schools of Music Self-Survey report, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 1)
- National Associations of Schools of Music Self-Survey report 1st Draft, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 2)
- NASM Self-Study Report, Spring 1985 (Box UP0005, Folder 3)
- Grad School, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 4)
- University, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 5)
- National Association of Schools of Music, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 6)
- National Association of Schools of Music, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 7)
- Commission on Undergraduate Studies, Administration, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 8)
- Music Dept., undated (Box UP0005, Folder 9)
- Applied Music Standards, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 10)
- Theory Book Extra Pages, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 11)
- Theory Booklets, Pianoforte Examinations, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 12)
- Alexandria Symphony in Concert 39th Season Programs, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 13)
- Alexandria Symphony in Concert Programs 79-82 season, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 14)
- Alexandria Symphony in Concert Programs 84-85 season, undated (Box UP0005, Folder 14)
- Clippings and Newsletters, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 1)
- Clippings, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 3)
- Music 208 Packet, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 4)
- Chamber Music Lit., undated (Box UP0006, Folder 4)
- Birth of Modernity, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 5)
- History of Music, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 6)
- Music 103- outline, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 7)
- Music 103- lists and class materials, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 8)
- Music 103- Reading Lists, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 9)
- History of Music 103- quizzes and exams, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 10)
- Program Notes, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 11)
- UN Youth Concert, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 12)
- "Triptych" Arthur Shepherd, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 13)
- WMTA, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 14)
- National Symphony Orchestra, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 15)
- MTNA, undated (Box UP0006, Folder 16)
- MTNA- Eastern Division Convention 1962 (Box UP0006, Folder 17)
- untitled 4 (Box UP0006, Folder 18)
- A.U. (Box UP0006, Folder 19)
- Letters rec. (Box UP0006, Folder 20)
- Letters of Acknowledgement (Box UP0006, Folder 21)
- Letter of appreciation (Box UP0006, Folder 22)
- MTNA- Eastern Division Convention 1964 (Box UP0006, Folder 23)
- History of education, Syllabus of History of Occidental Civilization, radio data handbook, practical drills in Keyboard Harmonics, Manuscript book, loose manuscripts, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 1)
- By Laws and Minutes of National Music Research Council, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 2)
- Recording Hemingway Nov. 1991 (Box UP0007, Folder 3)
- Music 4 AIDS, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 4)
- Elgiornazi, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 5)
- Grant, U.S. III, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 6)
- MUS 004, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 7)
- Stagebill, Washington Camerata, Letters, Alexandria Symphony Orchestra repertoire 1966-1987, Saint Louis Blues (Box UP0007, Folder 8)
- Staff Paper and scores, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 9)
- Navy Study Material, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 10)
- Mus 3 Aids, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 11)
- Mus Appre I, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 12)
- Newspaper clippings, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 13)
- Antonin Dvorak - Music 3, an introduction to music, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 14)
- Music 3, 1987 (Box UP0007, Folder 15)
- Music 208 Packet # 2, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 16)
- Steiner Packet No. 2 music 108, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 17)
- Reserve for Music 208, 20th century, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 18)
- Untitled: Music 208 Materials, undated (Box UP0007, Folder 19)
- Music Departmental 1977-78, 1977-1978 (Box UP0008, Folder 1)
- Music Departmental 1978-1979 (Box UP0008, Folder 2)
- Music Departmental 1979-1980 (Box UP0008, Folder 3)
- Music Departmental 1980-1981 (Box UP0008, Folder 4)
- Music Departmental 1981-1982 (Box UP0008, Folder 5)
- Columbian College 1969-82 (selected materials), 1969-1982 (Box UP0008, Folder 6)
- Budget Study Info 1970-71, 1970-1971 (Box UP0008, Folder 7)
- University General 1961 (Box UP0008, Folder 8)
- University General 1962 (Box UP0008, Folder 9)
- University General 1963 (Box UP0008, Folder 10)
- University General 1964-1965 (Box UP0008, Folder 11)
- University General 1965-1966 (Box UP0008, Folder 12)
- University General 1966-1967 (Box UP0008, Folder 13)
- University General 1967-1968 (Box UP0008, Folder 14)
- University General 1968-1969 (Box UP0008, Folder 15)
- University General 1969-1970 (Box UP0008, Folder 16)
- University General 1970-1971 (Box UP0008, Folder 17)
- University General 1971-1972 (Box UP0008, Folder 18)
- University General 1972-1973 (Box UP0008, Folder 19)
- University General 1973-1974 (Box UP0008, Folder 20)
- University General 1974-1975 (Box UP0008, Folder 21)
- University General 1975-1976 (Box UP0008, Folder 22)
- University General 1976-1977 (Box UP0008, Folder 23)
- University General 1977-1978 (Box UP0008, Folder 24)
- University General 1978-1979, 1978-1980 (Box UP0008, Folder 25)
- University General 1980-81, 1980-1981 (Box UP0008, Folder 26)
- University General 1981-1982 (Box UP0008, Folder 27)
- Title IV 68-69, 1968-1969 (Box UP0008, Folder 28)
- Title VI 1974-1975 (Box UP0008, Folder 29)
- Title VI 1975-1976 (Box UP0008, Folder 30)
- Title VI 1976-1977 (Box UP0008, Folder 31)
- Title VI 1977 (Box UP0008, Folder 32)
- Title VI 1978 (Box UP0008, Folder 33)
- Releases, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 34)
- Releases 1962 (Box UP0008, Folder 35)
- Academic Plan, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 36)
- Arts Club Scholarship, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 37)
- Chopin, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 38)
- Folk Music Society, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 39)
- Faculty Associate, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 40)
- GWU Club, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 41)
- Honors Committee, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 42)
- Inaugural Committee, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 43)
- Madrigal Singers, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 44)
- Library, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 45)
- Meyer Foundation, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 46)
- National Arts Council, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 47)
- 90-Hour Program, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 48)
- North Carolina, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 49)
- Paris Academy, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 50)
- Performing Arts Committee, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 51)
- Public Ceremonies Committee, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 52)
- Music Education, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 53)
- Committee on University Resources, undated (Box UP0008, Folder 54)
- Student Registration Totals Fall 1970-Spring 1978 (Box UP0008, Folder 55)
- Releases 1963 (Box UP0008, Folder 56)
- Releases 1964 (Box UP0008, Folder 57)
- Releases 1965-1966 (Box UP0008, Folder 58)
- Releases 1967-1968 (Box UP0008, Folder 59)
- Releases 1968-1969 (Box UP0008, Folder 60)
- Releases 1969-1970 (Box UP0008, Folder 61)
- Releases 1971 (Box UP0008, Folder 62)
- Union Methodist Church (Box UP0008, Folder 63)
- U.S. Recording Company (Box UP0008, Folder 64)
- University Center (Box UP0008, Folder 65)